Today's דף *daf* is י"ג *Yud Gimmel*, but we have a little
catching up to do.
So we start on י"ב עמוד ב' *Yud Bais Amud Bais* and
we're asking about different types of scenarios about what you can use
to redeem for the donkey. The משנה Mishnah. *Mishna* talked about sheep
that were hybrid and so on. So let's take a look at
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
איבעיא להו *Iba'ya lehu*, very top of י"ב עמוד ב' *Yud Bais
Amud Bais*, first line at the end of the line. איבעיא להו
*Iba'ya lehu*, they raised the question: מהו לפדות בבהמה של שביעית *Ma'u
lifdot behema shevi'it*?
Can you use a sheep that was purchased with שמיטה shemitah, *Shemita*
money? ודאי לא תיבעיא לך *Vaday lo tiba'ya lach*.
If you're redeeming a donkey that is definitely obligated, then you certainly
cannot use it. Why? Because you're giving the כהן kohen *Kohen* the
sheep instead of the donkey. So that is, although it's technically redemption,
it certainly has the appearance of a type of a purchase, of
an exchange. It's as if you're buying the donkey for the sheep
and you're using שמיטה shemitah *Shemita* produce to do a type of
a sale, you know, a commerce with.
So we did that.
Oh, you did that?
That's where we were.
Okay, so we'll do that quickly. כי תיבעיא לך ספק *Ki tiba'ya
lach safek*. So the question is, what if it is a doubtful
redemption where you're going to keep the sheep? So what should be
the issue? ואליבא דרבי שמעון לא תיבעיא לך דלית ליה ספק *Ve'aliba
de'Rabbi Shimon lo tiba'ya lach de'leis lei safek*. According to רבי שמעון
*Rabbi Shimon* there's no issue. He doesn't require redemption for a ספק
*safek* because רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says that the donkey has no
forbidden status and therefore the only reason you would redeem a ספק
*safek* is if it has a forbidden status in order to remove
it. So according to רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* it's a moot question,
there's no need to redeem a ספק *safek*. כי תיבעיא לך אליבא
דרבי יהודה *Ki tiba'ya lach aliba de'Rabbi Yehuda*. The question is according
to רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. מה *Ma*, what would you say? כיון
דמפריש לה לעצמו לאכילה קרינן ביה *Keivan de'mafrish leh le'atzmo la'achila karinan
bei*.
Since you separate out the sheep and you keep it, so you're
going to satisfy the שמיטה shemitah *Shemita* status of this sheep because
you're going to eat the sheep, you'll eventually slaughter it and eat
it, and big deal that you used it to do this act
of redeeming the donkey. או דילמא *O dilma*, or would we say,
כיון דכמה דלא מפקי איסורא לא משתרי *Keivan de'kama de'lo mafki issura
lo mishtarei*,
since without removing the status of the donkey, the donkey is still
forbidden, so כסחורה דמי *k'sechora dami*,
it's like a type of a commerce or exchange. Although you don't
give
the sheep to
the כהן kohen *Kohen*, since you use the sheep to redeem the
status of the donkey, it's like you're using it in a type
of a commerce and you're not allowed to use שמיטה shemitah *Shemita*
produce in commerce. So what would you say? תא שמע *Tashma*, come
and hear, דאמר רב Rav חסדא בהמה שביעית אין פודין בה ודאי
*de'amar Rav Chisda behema shevi'it ein podin bah vaday*. You cannot use
it for definite redemption because then by giving it to the כהן
kohen *Kohen* you really are doing a type of a commerce with
it. אבל פודין בה ספק *Aval podin bah safek*, you can do
doubtful redemption and that's according to obviously רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. רבי
שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* would never require it for doubtful because he says
there's no point. And therefore, and therefore you see that as long
as you're not giving it to the כהן kohen *Kohen* it's not
considered to be a type of a commerce and it is okay.
All right, now, ואמר *ve'amar*, now that we're talking about an animal
of שמיטה shemitah *Shemita*, we're going to have another הלכה halacha *halacha*
about it. ואמר רב Rav חסדא בהמה שביעית פטורה מן הבכורה וחייבת
במתנות *Ve'amar Rav Chisda behema shevi'it petura min habechora vechayaves bamatnot*. So
if it is a בהמה *behema* of שמיטה shemitah *Shemita*, it is
exempt from firstborn for the reason that we basically said that you
cannot use it as a type of an exchange.
But if you
שחט *shacht* it and eat it, you still have to give the
gifts, the זרוע לחיים וקיבה *zroa lechayayim vekeiva*, the arm and the
stomach and the maw, you have to give that to the כהן
kohen. *Kohen*. Why? פטורה מן הבכורה *Petura min habechora*, it's exempt from
בכורה *bechora*. לאכלה אמר amar, רחמנא ולא לשריפה *Le'achla amar rachmana velo
lesreifa*. Oh, I'm sorry. When we said it's exempt from בכורה *bechora*,
we meant not as a, not to exchange, but we meant if
it is a firstborn sheep or firstborn cow. Let's say you bought
a sheep or cow with שמיטה shemitah *Shemita* money and it
had a firstborn animal. So therefore, would that animal be obligated or
exempt? So here we're saying that it is exempt. Why is it
exempt? Because what do you have to do with a firstborn? You
have to bring it as a קרבן korban *korban* and you burn
the innards on the מזבח *mizbe'ach*, on the altar. So therefore the
שמיטה shemitah *Shemita* status requires that you eat it completely, not that
you burn part of it. So if you actually have a firstborn
that is itself purchased or has שמיטה shemitah קדושה *Shemita kedusha*, then
you do not bring it as a firstborn קרבן Korban. *korban* because
that would undermine, it does not have the sanctity of the firstborn
because that would contradict the sanctity of the שביעית *shevi'it* status which
obligates it be fully eaten and not part of it to be
burned. ולא לשריפה *Velo lesreifa*. וחייבת במתנות *Vechayaves bamatnot*, you do give
the portions to the כהן kohen *Kohen*. Why? לאכלה קרינן ביה *Le'achla
karinan bei*, because the כהן kohen *Kohen* will eat it. So גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, wait a minute, מיתיבי *meisvei*, I'll ask you on
this. האוכל מעיסת שביעית *Ha'ochel me'isa shevi'it*, if you eat from dough
that was made from שמיטה shemitah *Shemita* grain, עד שלא הורמה חלה
challah חייבת מיתה *ad she'lo hurma challa chayaves misa*. If you eat
it before the חלה challah *challa* was taken, then you're eating, you
have to take חלה challah *challa* from dough and if you don't,
it's like טבל *tevel*, it's like grain that you didn't take תרומות
ומעשרות *terumot u'ma'asrot* and you're punished by מיתה בידי שמים *misa bidei
shamayim*, heavenly death. So same true is true by dough that has
not had חלה challah *challa* taken from it and even if it's
שמיטה shemitah *Shemita* dough. ואמאי *Ve'amai*? So now גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
so that shows you that שמיטה shemitah *Shemita* dough is חייב *chayav*
in חלה challah *challa*. Now why is that true? Because it's possible
you might have to burn it. Why would you have to burn
it? If something טמא tamei, *tamei* touched the חלה challah *challa*, it
would have to be burned. So therefore why are
you
obligated? take off the חלה challah, it gets a status of like
תרומה terumah and if you touch that that would be have to
be burned. So לאכלה אמר רחמנא ולא לשרפה. l'achlah amar rachmana v'lo
l'sreifah. So it has to be eaten, not burned. So you should
not be obligated in חלה challah because by being obligated in חלה
it might wind up that you might have to burn it. And
since it might wind up that you have to burn it and
you're not allowed to do that with שמיטה, shemitah so therefore maybe
the entire שמיטה shemitah dough should be exempt from the
מצוה mitzvah of חלה because that would possibly run up against the
idea of having to burn it. So the גמרא Gemara says here's
the answer. The answer is obvious what the difference is. So let's
take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, שאני הכא דכתיב לדורותיכם. shani hacha
d'chtiv l'doroteichem.
There it's different that the verse says that you should do the
מצוה mitzvah of חלה for your future generations and that has a
sense of sort of greater scope, so it means even during the
שמיטה shemitah year. Now the more obvious answer is coming up. The
גמרא Gemara says תניא נמי הכי, tanya nami hachi, it taught so
as well. מנין לאוכל מעיסת שביעית שלא הורמה חלתה שחייב מיתה? minayin
l'ochel m'isat shevi'it shelo hurma challatah shechayav mitah?
How do you know if you eat from שמיטה shemitah. dough before
the חלה was taken you're חייב מיתה, chayav mitah, meaning that there's
still a מצוה mitzvah to take חלה from שמיטה shmitah, dough? שנאמר
לדורותיכם, shenemar l'doroteichem,
for your future generations, which means it applies even during the שמיטה
year. And now וליגמר מינה, v'ligmar minah, why not learn from that
also to other types of things like a בכור, bechor, that you
give a בכור bechor even if it has שמיטה status? Who cares
if part of it is burned? Once it has שמיטה status and
you just ignore the part that's burned. So the obvious difference is
clear and the גמרא Gemara says it. No, התם עיקר אכילה הכא
עיקר לשרפה. hatam ikar achilah hacha ikar l'sreifah. There
by the dough primarily if everything goes right the כהן kohen will
eat the חלה, you'll eat the dough, nothing will be burned, it'll
all be eaten. So therefore שמיטה can apply to the dough because
if things go right you're not going to be forced to burn
it and you'll be able to eat the whole thing. So therefore
even if it's שמיטה dough you can have the status of חלה
because it doesn't necessarily contradict the שמיטה status. But by a בכור
bechor the basic מצוה mitzvah is is that you bring the בכור
bechor as a קרבן Korban. and you burn the innards. So therefore
the basic מצוה mitzvah of בכור bechor goes against the status of
שמיטה which will require that something be burned. And since שמיטה does
not allow it to be burned, demands that it all be eaten,
therefore if you have an animal that is a שמיטה animal, obviously
it doesn't mean it grew from the ground but it was purchased
with שמיטה funds, the מצוה mitzvah of בכור bechor does not apply
because that would contradict the מצוה mitzvah of שמיטה. You had a
question? Okay. Alright, so now let's finish up the משנה. Mishnah תנינא
להא דתנו רבנן. tanina l'ha d'tanu rabanan. Now, נתנו לכהן, netano l'kohen,
if you give it to the כהן kohen the משנה Mishnah says
the חמור chamor you have to see the כהן kohen redeem it.
You can't trust the כהן kohen to redeem the בכור, bechor, the
חמור. chamor. He might just decide hey, I'm going to get the
sheep anyway if I redeem it, why should I bother redeeming it?
I'll just use the donkey. Okay, and that's obviously forbidden because a
donkey is forbidden in benefit even to the כהן. Kohen So the
גמרא Gemara says תנינא להא דתנו רבנן, tanina l'ha d'tanu rabanan, we've
learned our משנה Mishnah and we've learned the ברייתא. Braitah. ישראל שהיה
לו פטר חמור בתוך ביתו, Yisrael she-hayah lo peter chamor b'toch beito,
if an ישראל, Yisrael, if a non-כהן Kohen has a firstborn donkey
in his house, ואמר לו הכהן תנהו לי, v'amar lo ha-kohen tnehu
li, and the כהן Kohen says to him, you know what, don't
bother redeeming it, just give it straight to me, ואני אפרנו, v'ani
efdenu, I'll redeem it. Now first of all that might not be
in your best financial interest because we already learned that you can
redeem it with a sheep of lesser value. But let's say you
don't have a sheep of lesser value, you don't want to שלעפ,
shlep, כהן Kohen is just saying just give it to me, I'll
take care of it. So it says הרי זה לא יתננו לו,
harei zeh lo yitnenu lo, don't give it to him. We're afraid
that he'll wind up using the donkey without bothering to redeem it.
Even though it really won't cost him any money to redeem it,
right, he just has a sheep, he gets to use both of
them, but he won't bother, he'll figure heck I have them both
anyway, who needs to redeem it? אלא אם כן פדהו בפניו, ela
im ken padahu b'fanav, you're only allowed to do it if he
you see him redeeming it in your presence. אמר רב נחמן אמר
רבה בר אבוה, amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha, so רב
נחמן Rav Nachman says זאת אומרת נחשדו כהנים על פטרי חמורים. zot
omeret nechshedu kohanim al pitrei chamorim. This tells you that כהנים kohanim
are suspect for you know not following the laws of firstborn donkeys,
of using them even when they're forbidden in benefit. Because obviously that's
why you can't trust him, because he's suspect, because you're afraid he'll
figure heck it's mine anyway, why should I bother? So the גמרא
Gemara says פשיטא, p'shita, obviously, that's the whole point, what are you
telling us? No, מהו דתימא, mahu d'teima, I might have thought that
that teaching in the משנה mishna. and the ברייתא Braitah was a
special case. הני מילי היכא דמחזק לן דמכרי. hani mili heicha d'muchzak
lan d'michrei. That's when we have a pattern and we see that
it's occurred. We see that once or twice it happened that somebody
has given him a donkey and he wound up using it without
redeeming it. So there maybe we would say don't trust him, don't
give it to him unless you see him redeeming it. אבל בסתם
לא, aval b'stam lo, but maybe I would think the norm is
maybe we are allowed to trust them. קא משמע לן, ka mashma
lan, this is teaching us דמורה בהיתירא, d'moreh b'heteira, that he he
teaches for himself, he rationalizes. He you know he tells himself look,
in the end I'm going to redeem it, I'm going to keep
the sheep, I'm going to keep the donkey, so why not just
go ahead and use the donkey right now? And therefore since they
will rationalize that way you only wait till they actually redeem it.
And what's interesting about this is is it's never made explicit in
this פרק perek and you know not really so discussed as I
could see elsewhere, is the תורה Torah never says that the כהן
Kohen? is entitled to the donkey, right? The כהן Kohen, says you
either give a כהן Kohen, a sheep or... So why not just
go ahead and use the donkey right now? And therefore, since they
would rationalize that way, you only wait until they actually redeem. And
what's interesting about this is, although never made explicit in this פרק
perek and not really so discussed as I could see elsewhere, is
the תורה Torah never says that the כהן Kohen. is entitled to
the donkey, right? The תורה Torah says you either give a כהן
Kohen a sheep or you break the neck. So actually, I would
have thought if the כהן Kohen, asks for a donkey, even assuming
that they were not suspect, you break the neck. So actually, I
would have thought if the כהן Kohen. asks for a donkey, even
assuming that they were not suspect,
why am I even why do I even fulfill my מצוה mitzvah
by giving the donkey to the כהן? Kohen. Let's assume that I
trust him, I see him redeem it, etc. Why do I do
my מצוה? mitzvah? The תורה Torah tells me my מצוה mitzvah is
to give him a sheep, right? So it is interesting here that
because there is this idea of redeeming, and actually the גמרא Gemara
even extended the idea of redeeming to value and not just a
sheep, that as I saw the way one of the אחרונים acharonim
articulated it is as if it's as if the donkey belongs to
the כהן, Kohen but that's not really true, it's the sheep that
belongs to the כהן, Kohen not the donkey. The proof being that
if the donkey dies,
then I don't give the dead donkey to the כהן. Kohen, I
can't use it, it's אסור בהנאה. assur be-hana'ah. But anyway, it's quite
interesting the assumption here that I could fulfill my מצוה mitzvah by
giving the donkey to the כהן Kohen and the only concern is
will he satisfy his obligation. Why I should assume that I can
fulfill my מצוה, mitzvah, I don't know, maybe we assume it's intuitive
since I do it by giving him a substitute, but anyway, it's
certainly not explicit. Let's take a look now at the next משנה.
Mishnah המפריש פדיון פטר חמור ומת. Ha-mafrish pidyon peter chamor u-met. You
separated out the first-born donkey and then it died. רבי אליעזר אומר
חייבין באחריותן. Rabbi Eliezer omer chayavin be-achrayutan. So here רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says you have not done the מצוה mitzvah of redeeming the
firstborn
until after I'm sorry not the donkey died I got that I'm
sorry excuse me the sheep died. Now he says you do not
do the מצוה mitzvah of redeeming the firstborn donkey until you give
the sheep to the כהן, Kohen? like by when you do a
redemption of a firstborn child. If you separate out the five שקל,
shekel, you haven't done the מצוה. mitzvah. The מצוה mitzvah is only
when you give the money to the כהן. Kohen, That's why we
actually make the ברכה beracha when the money is handed over to
the כהן. Kohen, So here, let's say you separated out the sheep
and the sheep died. Have I said I've done my מצוה, mitzvah,
here כהן Kohen, take a dead sheep? Or have I said no,
I haven't done my מצוה, mitzvah, so I have to give the
כהן Kohen, a live sheep because the redemption is only when it's
alive? So that's the debate. So
רבי אליעזר אומר חייבין באחריותן. Rabbi Eliezer omer chayavin be-achrayutan. You
are obligated in the liability of the sheep
כחמש סלעים של בן ke-chamesh sela'im shel ben and therefore until it's
handed over your מצוה mitzvah is not yet complete. וחכמים אומרים אין
חייבין באחריותן. Va-chachamim omrim ein chayavin be-achrayutan. You are not obligated in
the liability
כפדיון מעשר שני. ke-pidyon ma'aser sheni. Just like when you redeem מעשר
שני, ma'aser sheni, if I have crops that grew in the third
and sixth year and I redeem it in order to bring the
money to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, I redeem it on money and then the
money gets lost, I don't have to use new money. Once the
status is transferred to the money, I'm done. Then I have to
bring the money to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, but if it gets lost, I
don't have to do it again. So here too, once you put
it on the sheep, you're done with your you're done, it's been
redeemed. You're supposed to now give the sheep to the כהן, Kohen,
but your redemption, the act of redemption is done as soon as
you do that. העיד רבי יהושע ורבי צדוק. He'id Rabbi Yehoshua ve-Rabbi
Tzadok. רבי יהושע ורבי צדוק Rabbi Yehoshua ve-Rabbi Tzadok gave testimony על
פדיון פטר חמור שמת al pidyon peter chamor she-met that if the
donkey died שאין לכהן כלום. she-ein la-kohen klum. The כהן Kohen. gets
nothing. I mean he gets the dead sheep, but he doesn't really
get a new sheep instead. You've done your מצוה mitzvah when you
have redeemed it. מת פטר חמור. Met peter chamor. Now what happens
if the donkey died before you gave the sheep to the כהן?
Kohen So here the positions would be reversed. רבי אליעזר אומר יקבר
ומותר בהנאה של פלד. Rabbi Eliezer omer yikaver u-mutar be-hana'ah shel peled.
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
says
since you haven't given the sheep yet to the כהן, Kohen, although
you set it aside, but you haven't given it yet, it hasn't
been redeemed. So if the donkey hasn't yet been redeemed, so it's
still forbidden in benefit. So what do you do if the donkey
died? You bury it. But here's the positive. You get to keep
the sheep because now it's like since it hasn't been redeemed till
you give the sheep to the כהן, Kohen it's like the donkey
died before any redemption was done. So fine, you can't get benefit,
but there's no longer a מצוה mitzvah to redeem it once it's
dead. So you get to keep the sheep. That's what רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says. וחכמים אומרים אין צריך לקבר. Va-chachamim omrim ein tzarich
le-ikaver.
You don't have to bury it. As soon as you designated the
sheep, the forbidden status was removed. So therefore, the donkey is now
even as a dead donkey you could derive benefit, turn it into
dog food, whatever. Redemption occurred as soon as you designated the sheep.
But of course because the redemption already occurred, who gets the sheep?
The כהן, kohen because it's already been redeemed. והיא לכהן Ve-hi la-kohen
in cases like this.
So here you have a very consistent debate, when is the act
of redemption? When you set aside the sheep, that's what the חכמים
Chachamim say, that's the way we rule. So in that case if
the sheep dies tough luck for the כהן, kohen if the donkey
dies tough luck for you. Or only when you give it over
to the כהן, kohen that's what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says. Since
we rule it's when the sheep is set aside, תוספות Tosafot says
that's for when when you make the ברכה beracha for פדיון הבן,
pidyon ha-ben, you make it when the money is given to the
כהן. When you make a ברכה beracha for פדיון פטר חמור, pidyon
peter chamor, you make it when the sheep is designated, because that's
when the מצוה mitzvah is done. So let's take a look. אמר
רב יוסף. Amar Rav Yosef. Said רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. מאי טעמא
דרבי אליעזר? mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Eliezer? What's the reason of רבי אליעזר?
Rabbi Eliezer? דכתיב. de-chtiv. The פסוק pasuk says
אך פדה תפדה. ach padoh tifdeh. You should surely redeem. מה בכור
אדם חייב באחריותו אף בכור בהמה טמאה חייב באחריותו. mah bechor adam
chayav be-achrayuto af bechor behemah teme'ah chayav be-achrayuto. The same way the
firstborn of humans you're obligated in its liability until you hand it
over, the מצוה mitzvah isn't done until it's handed over, here too.
by a donkey, the מצוה’s mitzvah not done until the sheep is
handed over. So אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye
said back, אם בכור אדם מותר בהנאה בכור בהמה טמאה מותר בהנאה?
im bechor adam mutar be-hana’ah bechor behema teme’ah mutar be-hana’ah? One minute,
we don’t obviously make the whole comparison because if we were to
make the full comparison we would say the same way there’s no
prohibition on deriving benefits from humans’ firstborn until they’ve been redeemed, why
don’t we say the same is true about donkeys and it’s clear
from the משנה Mishnah, that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer agrees that donkeys
are forbidden in benefit until they’re redeemed. וכי תימא הכא נמי ve-chi
teima hacha nami lest you say that that’s true, we should do
make that parallel, והתנן ve-hasnan we teach in a משנה, mishna מת
פטר חמור meis peter chamor if the donkey died, רבי אליעזר אומר
יקבר Rabbi Eliezer omer yikaver it gets buried. So you see that
right it says if it dies before you hand over the sheep,
so redemption hasn’t taken place, it gets buried. So you see that
he says that the donkey is forbidden in benefit. So it’s not
totally like a human, a human is permissible in benefit before he’s
redeemed. So וכי תימא ve-chi teima unless you say
הכא נמי, hacha nami, so
מאי יקבר mai yikaver what does it mean you bury it? לאו
דאסור בהנאה lav de-assur be-hana’ah doesn’t that show you it’s forbidden in
benefit that you bury it? So you see that רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says it’s not exactly like a human. גמרא Gemara says לא
יקבר כבכור אדם. lo yikaver ke-bechor adam. No, you bury it, why
do you bury it? The same way you would bury a human
who died. Since it’s compared to a human you bury it like
you bury humans, which is crazy, I mean it’s not you bury
it’s not because you’re burying it because of its בכור bechor status
now, it’s burying it because it’s compared to humans that you bury
humans. So the גמרא Gemara does not like that. The גמרא Gemara
says אלא אדם בכור הוא דבעי קבורה ella adam bechor hu de-ba’i
kvura what do you mean? You mean by humans you only bury
firstborn people that
die? So פשוט לא בעי קבורה pashut lo ba’i kvura a non-firstborn
you don’t bury? So that’s crazy, you don’t bury it because it’s
like a firstborn human. It’s anyway it’s not about the humans, it’s
not about their firstborn status that means why you bury them. ועוד
תניא ve-od tanya we taught in a ברייתא, Baraisa, מודה רבי אליעזר
בישראל, modeh Rabbi Eliezer be-Yisrael, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer agrees in a
non-כהן שיש לו ספק פטר חמור בתוך ביתו. she-yesh lo safek peter
chamor besoch beiso. He has a doubtful firstborn donkey, right? So what
do you do with a doubtful firstborn donkey? You redeem it with
the sheep and you keep the sheep. So what do you do?
Now the problem is here’s the question according to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi
Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you only do the מצוה mitzvah
of redemption when you hand over the sheep. But there’s one case
where you do a redemption without ever handing over the sheep. When?
When it’s a doubt. So since it’s a doubt you don’t have
to hand the sheep to the כהן, okay, and there how would
you remove the status from the donkey if according to רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer the מצוה mitzvah of redemption is not done until the
sheep is handed over? So there he says no, since in that
case you’re not obligated to hand it over, since in civil law
you’re entitled to keep it because המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה hamotzi me-chavero
alav ha-raya the burden of proof is on the other person, so
therefore in that case he says you actually the redemption does complete
when you just do the designation. When you have to hand it
over the designation is the redemption is not done until you hand
over. When you don’t because it’s a doubt the redemption is done
at the moment of the designation. So therefore we say
so this is what we teach in the ברייתא. Baraisa. מודה רבי
אליעזר בישראל שיש לו ספק פטר חמור בתוך ביתו modeh Rabbi Eliezer
be-Yisrael she-yesh lo safek peter chamor besoch beiso he has a doubtful
donkey in his house, שמפריש עליו שה she-mafrish alo she that he
separates out a sheep, והוא שלו ve-hu shelo and he keeps it
and the redemption is done. Anyway the point why that’s relevant for
us besides being interesting within רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that when you
don’t hand over the sheep the redemption is done in an earlier
stage is because it shows that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer admits that
the donkey is forbidden in benefit or else you wouldn’t bother doing
the redemption. So how does רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer say he says
that the reason you don’t fulfill the finish the redemption till you
hand it to the כהן is similar to the firstborn human you
don’t do redemption till you hand the money, so why doesn’t he
compare completely to the human and say it’s permissible in benefit? Why
does he say that the donkey is forbidden in benefit? So the
גמרא Gemara says אלא אמר רבא אמר קרא ella amar Rava amar
kra because the verse says אך פדה תפדה ach padoh tifteh you
shall surely redeem it, לפדיה היא הוקש ולא לדבר אחר. le-fdiya hi
hukash velo le-davar acher.
When is the human compared to donkeys or donkeys to humans? For
the act of redemption, both of them are redeemed, not fully. Obviously
you redeem them with different things and etc. So basically the act
of redemption. So yes it’s true donkeys are forbidden in benefit, humans
are permissible, but רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says the same way humans
you don’t do the מצוה mitzvah till you hand over the money,
by donkeys you don’t do the redemption till you hand over the
sheep assuming you are going to hand over the sheep, it’s not
a case of doubt. And according to him then you would make
the ברכה bracha for the donkeys even when you hand over the
sheep. We rule that donkeys you redeem the מצוה mitzvah is done
when you designate the sheep, not when you hand it over and
therefore again as I said תוספות Tosafos says you make the ברכה
bracha even before you hand it over. תנן התם. Tnan hasam. Now
we’re going to end this discussion with an important question, also question
about comparing it to humans, about when does the מצוה mitzvah of
redeeming the donkeys begin and end. By humans we know it begins
at thirty days. How about by donkeys? We had said in an
earlier גמרא Gemara it begins immediately but now we’re going to see
that’s a matter of debate. So let’s take a look. We taught
over there, הערכין בשעתן ha-erachin ba-sha’atan
when you if I say the ערך erech of somebody I accept
upon myself a vow to give the ערך erech of somebody which
is a chart in the תורה Torah how much you give based
on age and sex. So let’s say by the time I get
around to paying the person is older, okay, and he’s now in
a different his value places him differently on the chart than when
I took the vow. Nevertheless you give the amount based on when
the moment you took the vow, not the moment you pay. That’s
what it means בשעתן. ba-sha’atan. ופדיון הבן אחר שלשים יום u-pidyon ha-ben
achar shloshim yom you do the פדיון הבן pidyon ha-ben when he’s
thirty days old. ופדיון פטר חמור. u-pidyon peter chamor. ופדיון פטר חמור
לאלתר, u'pidyon peter chamor l'altar, and you do donkeys immediately. So now
the גמרא Gemara says, okay, that's a pretty explicit. And why not?
The תורה Torah doesn't say thirty days, it just says redeem it.
So now the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, ופדיון פטר חמור u'pidyon
peter chamor לאלתר, l'altar, is that really true that you do it
immediately? ורמינהו, v'reminhu, ask on this, אין בערכין ובפדיון הבן ובנזירות ובפטר
חמור פחות משלשים יום משלשים. ein b'erchin u'vidyon haben u'vnezirut u'vpeter chamor
pachot mishloshim yom mishloshim. We have a ברייתא braita that says that
when it comes to ערך, erech, the value of a human, the
תורה Torah starts giving value, you know, on that chart
once somebody is thirty days old. If somebody said the ערך erech
of this infant, less than thirty days, it's on me, then they're
not on the chart, you don't give the value. So values of
humans only begin at thirty days. פדיון הבן pidyon haben obviously only
begins at thirty days. נזירות, nezirut, a standard נזירות nezirut of somebody
not going to drink wine or become טמא, minimum נזירות nezirut is
thirty days. And פטר חמור peter chamor is minimum thirty days. So
what does that mean פטר חמור peter chamor is minimum thirty days?
It sounds like פטר חמור peter chamor does not start until the
donkey is thirty days old. How did that go, how did that
compare to the previous statement, which said that it starts immediately? And
then the end of this ברייתא braita says ומוסיפין עליו, v'osifin alav,
but those things go ad infinitum. Once it's thirty days, it keeps
on going. Obviously you could have a נזירות nezirut for your entire
life, you could have the value of a human until however old
he is, right? You could do the redeeming of the firstborn son
after thirty days. If somebody was never had a פדיון הבן, pidyon
haben, they could do it when they're an adult. So those things
keep on going, but they start at thirty days, or thirty days
is the minimum. So there it says not immediately by firstborn donkey,
thirty days. How do you resolve this? So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר רב נחמן לומר שאם פדאו פדוי. amar Rav Nachman lomar she'im
pedao padui. You're right, it really does start at thirty days by
a donkey. When it says immediately, it means בדיעבד, b'diavad, post facto,
if you did it earlier than thirty days, it still works. So
the גמרא Gemara. says, one minute, מכלל דבנו אם פדאו אינו פדוי.
mikhlal d'vno im pedao eino padui. It contrasts a donkey to humans.
So if you're saying that when it says a donkey immediately means
even post facto it works prior than thirty days, then the comparison
would say that by humans even post facto would not work less
than thirty days. והאיתמר, veha'itmar, did we not say, הפודה בנו בתוך
שלשים יום, hapodeh bno b'tokh shloshim yom, if you jump the gun
and you did a redeeming of your son less than thirty days,
רב Rav אמר בנו פדוי, amar bno padui, it does work בדיעבד.
b'diavad. So then there is no difference. Both humans and donkeys, you're
not supposed to do until thirty days, but if you did it,
it works. So the גמרא Gemara says, no no no, it doesn't
really work by humans. לאיתמר, l'itmar, we qualified that statement of רב
and we said, אמר רבא דכולי עלמא מעכשיו אין בנו פדוי. amar
Rava d'khulei alma me'akhshav ein bno padui. If you try to say
my son is redeemed today and it's less than thirty days, it
does not work. When did רב say it works less than thirty
days? If I take out the five shekalim and I say this
will be for the redemption of my son two weeks from now
when he's thirty days old. So you did the act now, but
you said it should only take effect later.
And why would we need a חדוש chiddush for that? Isn't that
kind of obvious?
No, it's not so obvious, and we'll talk about it when we
get to בכור אדם bekhor adam later. But for now the important
thing is that if you actually try to make it take effect
prior than thirty days, it would not work. And therefore we're saying,
but by donkeys it does work. So we now have this contradiction.
One statement says donkeys work immediately, the other thirty days. One way
of resolving it is you're supposed to wait till thirty days. If
you did it immediately, it works, and it is different than humans
in that respect because humans, if you did it, tried to do
everything immediately, it does not work. Maybe you could do it now
to take effect later, that we'll discuss, and it's not as obvious,
so obvious, but we'll discuss that later. So that's one answer, that
donkeys you're supposed to wait till thirty days but post facto it
works. Top of י"ג עמוד א'. yud gimmel amud alef. רב ששת
אמר לומר שאינו עובר עליו. Rav Sheshet amar lomar she'eino over alav.
No, רב ששת Rav Sheshet says here's what it means. What it
means is it really is immediately. What does it mean when it
says
thirty days? It means that until thirty days you haven't transgressed, okay?
You haven't so it's the exact sort of, if you would be
the exact inverse of humans. Humans starts at thirty days, he's reading
it donkeys start immediately, but after thirty days then already it's like
you've transgressed. What does it mean it continues forever? It means I
guess you keep on transgressing forever until you get it done. Now
that's a little bit of a strange idea because the תורה Torah
never says thirty days by donkeys. If we learned it out from
humans, we would say it starts at thirty days. Where should we
get an idea that says that you transgress at thirty days? Okay,
but that's how רב ששת Rav Sheshet is reconciling the two statements.
Let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with this. מתיבי רמי בר
חמא, metivei Rami bar Chama, רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama asks
on this by a תוספתא, Tosefta, מצותו כל שלשים יום. mitzvato kol
shloshim yom. The מצוה mitzvah of donkeys is all the first thirty
days. מכאן ואילך mikan va'eilakh after the thirty days, או פודהו, o
podehu, either make your choice. Meaning you've got a choice the first
thirty days what you're gonna do. Okay, once thirty days are up,
then it's like fish or cut bait. Either redeem the donkey או
עורפו o orefo or break its neck, one or the other. Stop
dilly-dallying. So מאי לאו, mai lav, is not this the way to
read that
ברייתא? braita? מצוה להשהותו כל שלשים יום. mitzva lehashoto kol shloshim yom.
That you wait thirty days because the מצוה mitzvah doesn't begin until
day thirty. So ממש mamash it doesn't start immediately. Everything begins on
day thirty. So therefore the first thirty days is you have time
to make your decision because the מצוה mitzvah is only going to
kick in on day thirty and then on day thirty you get
to decide are you going to redeem it or break its neck?
So you see it's not immediately and not like רב ששת Rav
Sheshet says. So the גמרא Gemara. says.
No, the way Sheshet would read this is it says מצווה לפדותו
כל שלושים יום. mitzvah liftoso kol shloshim yom. The first 30 days
is when you're supposed to redeem it. Okay, but if that's true,
what do you do with the end of the ברייתא? brayta? אי
הכי, I hachi, if that's true, how come the end says מכאן
ואילך או פודהו או עובר עליו? mikan ve'eilach o podehu o over
alav? מיבעי ליה. mibaylei. According to רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, it should
have said after 30 days, either redeem it or you'll transgress. It
shouldn't have said either redeem it or break the neck. According to
רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, right, as long as once it's after 30
days, you've already transgressed, you had to get it done within 30
days. So that ברייתא brayta does not work according to רב ששת.
Rav Sheshet. So, cause that ברייתא brayta sounds like after 30 days
you can still take your time to make your decision. Whereas according
to רב ששת Rav Sheshet you transgress immediately.
אלא אמר רבא, Ela amar Rava, rather רבא Rava says, לא קשיא.
Lo kashya. We have one ברייתא brayta that says, a משנה mishna.
that says immediately, we have a ברייתא brayta that says 30 days,
here's how we're going to resolve it. And this is a very
nice tie-in to what we taught in the משנה. mishna הא רבי
אליעזר דמקיש הא רבנן דלא מקשי. Ha Rabbi Eliezer demakish ha rabanan
d'lo makshi. One is רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that compares donkeys to
humans, one is the רבנן rabanan that don't compare donkeys to humans.
So how does that work? רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that compares donkeys
to humans and says the redemption does not take place till you
hand over the sheep, the same way it doesn't take place for
humans till you hand over the money, he would also say that
just like humans the מצווה mitzvah doesn't apply till the human baby
is 30 days old, it doesn't apply to the donkey till it's
30 days old. The רבנן rabanan that do not make the comparison
and they say the redemption is done as soon as you redeem
it on the sheep before you hand it over, so if the
sheep dies it's not your loss it's the כהן's loss. Okay, the
reverse, if the donkey dies then you still have to give the
sheep to the כהן because it took place as soon as you
did the redemption. Those same רבנן rabanan say they're not similar to
humans. Humans is only when you give the money over. Because it's
not similar, the מצווה mitzvah applies right away. Once you say that,
one minute, how do you deal with this תוספתא? tosefta? So here
the רמב"ם Rambam says, I think some אחרונים achronim have a difficulty
with it, but I think it's the best read of the גמרא.
Gemara The רמב"ם Rambam says, so now the תוספתא tosefta is not
a problem at all. The תוספתא tosefta is according to the רבנן.
rabanan. And the תוספתא tosefta says that you have 30, the מצווה
mitzvah begins immediately, right, כל שלושים יום, kol shloshim yom, the first
30 days the מצווה mitzvah applies, it applies immediately and is ongoing
the first 30 days. And the only point is, once 30 days
is up, maybe not based on a biblical verse, but once 30
days up is we don't let you tarry. We're going to insist
that you make a decision. You're not, ah, so that's what the
רמב"ם Rambam says. So the רמבם Rambam says after 30 days all
you have is שיהוי מצווה, shihuy mitzvah, you're just delaying doing the
מצווה, mitzvah, but you're not עובר. over. Now some אחרונים achronim ask,
but the גמרא Gemara said עובר עליו. over alav. But the point
is, that was within רב ששת. Rav Sheshet. Actually it works very
nicely according to the רמב"ם. Rambam. The מצווה mitzvah begins immediately, I
mean that's the מסקנא maskana of רבא. Rava. The מצווה mitzvah begins
immediately. At the end of 30 days we're going to ask you
to make up your mind. Don't keep on postponing it forever. But
if you do wind up dilly-dallying, you've delayed doing a מצווה mitzvah
but you haven't transgressed, because there's no reason that 30 days should
be a cutoff, right? Because we don't compare it to humans. There's
never a 30-day cutoff. The מצווה mitzvah begins immediately, but after a
certain point we ask you to make up your mind. Okay, so
that's the רבנן. rabanan. And again, the upshot of that is, is
that if you do פטר חמור, peter chamor, you don't make a
ברכה bracha when you give the money over because the, you make
the ברכה bracha when you do the redemption before you give it,
because that's when the מצווה mitzvah is done. We end with a
little bit of an anomaly, a משנה mishna that has no גמרא
Gemara. on it. Okay, so that's very rare. Of course partly it's
a printer's decision because the printer could have just added this משנה
mishna to the previous משנה mishnah and then we would have ended
with גמרא. Gemara But at any rate, let's take a look. לא
רצה לפדותו, Lo ratza liftoso, now if you do not want to
redeem it, ערפו מאחוריו, arfo me'achorav, you break its neck from behind.
We said before you use like a hatchet, not like a
saw. וקוברו, Vekovro, and you bury it because it's forbidden in benefit.
מצוות פדייה קודמת למצוות עריפה. Mitzvat pidyah kodemet lemitzvat arifah. Ah, pretty
obvious, you're supposed to redeem it before you break its neck, meaning
it's not like, oh, I can do either, I like inflicting pain
on animals, I'll break its neck. No, that's only if you're not
doing what you're supposed to do. You're supposed to redeem it. This
is a, this is a punishment if you don't do that. So
you're supposed to first redeem it. שנאמר אם לא תפדה, Shene'emar im
lo tifdeh, if you don't redeem, then וערפתו, ve'arafto, then you break
its neck. But that's not the idea. מצוות ייעוד קודמת למצוות הפדייה.
Mitzvat yi'ud kodemet lemitzvat hapidyah. Now that we're going to have a
couple of things like this, and the גמרא Gemara has decided that
it's not going to go into these because that's a digression. It
goes into them somewhere else. So the idea of if a man
takes a Jewish female woman as a slave woman under בת מצווה
bat mitzvah basically, what? A young girl, right, then he, then when
before she gets בת מצווה bat mitzvah basically his choice whether to
turn the purchase into קידושין, kidushin, which is ייעוד, yi'ud, or whether
to let her go free. So it says ideally you're supposed to
first do ייעוד, yi'ud, you're supposed to because presumably again in that
society and the whole idea that a father could marry off his
daughter underage or sell his daughter as a slave underage reflected a
reality of a certain social-economic reality and it was to protect the
financial interests and the well-being of his daughter to ensure she'd be
protected and cared for. And therefore the goal ultimately of this idea
was for him to marry her. So מצוות ייעוד, Mitzvat yi'ud, the
idea of making her into a wife, קודמת למצוות פדייה, kodemet lemitzvat
pidyah, comes before redeeming her and letting her go free. שנאמר אשר
לא יעדה, Shene'emar asher lo ye'adah, if he does not make her
his wife, then והפדה, vehefdah, then she shall be redeemed. מצוות יבום
קודמת למצוות חליצה. Mitzvat yibum kodemet lemitzvat chalitzah. ייבום Yibum of a,
the wife of a dead brother who has no children. ...comes before
חליצה. chalitzah. Obviously, the whole חליצה chalitzah ritual sort of is a
disgrace, right? This is what is done to a man who does
not establish the name of his brother's seed, and spits in on
the floor in front of him, so clearly that is that's not
what he should be doing, he should be doing יבום. yibum. בראשונה
Barishonah כשהיו מתכוונים לשם מצוה. kshehayu miskavnim l'shem mitzvah. Now that's what
we used to teach, originally when people did יבום yibum for the
sake of heaven. They did it because in order to establish the
name of their brothers and they did it for the sake of
the מצוה. mitzvah. But it says עכשיו achshav now that, oh wait,
עכשיו שאין מתכוונים לשם מצוה achshav she'ein miskavnim l'shem mitzvah now they
don't do it for the sake of the מצוה. mitzvah. They do
it because let's say, oh, I'll do יבום, yibum, my brother's wife
is attractive, or she has property, or something like that, doing it
for more sort of this-worldly concerns. So in that type of a
case they said you're not supposed to do יבום yibum because that's
not supposed to be the motivation. And it almost, the גמרא Gemara.
in one place in יבמות Yevamos goes so far as to say
it's almost as if you're transgressing the prohibition of sleeping with your
brother's wife, right? I mean the whole point about יבום yibum is
that otherwise this woman would be forbidden, would be an עריות, arayos,
a forbidden sexual relationship, but the מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum redefines
it. Redefines it as no, no, no, that's not what's going on
here, what's going on is you're being מקיים שם אחיו המת. mekayem
shem achiv hames. So it says but if that's not how you're
contextualizing it and how you're motivated, then although technically you're not doing
an עבירה, aveirah, it much more puts it under the ambit of
that עבירה aveirah because it's not לשמה lishmah but שלא לשמה. shelo
lishmah. What about that? Yeah, well, anyway, so that's one opinion in
the גמרא. Gemara There are other opinions by the way that say
it doesn't really matter what your motivation is, and actually interestingly, even
if you did it like כנה, kenah, all these other crazy... In
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and ספרדים, Sefardim, actually there's a major מחלוקת
machlokes how we פוסקים pasken about this in יבמות. Yevamos. So when
we learn יבמות Yevamos we'll discuss, talk about it, but ספרדים Sefardim
actually פוסקים pasken מצות יבום קודמת. mitzvas yibum kodemes. Okay? And ספרדים
Sefardim actually will do יבום yibum from time to time. So, anyway,
but this משנה mishnah says now that they're not doing it לשם
מצוה, l'shem mitzvah, אמרו מצות חליצה קודמת amru mitzvas chalitzah kodemes because
חליצה chalitzah comes first, the מצות יבום. mitzvas yibum. מצות הגאולה באדון
הוא קודם לכל אדם. Mitzvas hage'ulah b'adon hu kodem l'chol adam. If
you sanctify a property, then you're supposed to redeem it before other
people redeem it, שנאמר shene'emar as the verse says ואם לא יגאל
ונמכר בערכך. v'im lo yiga'el v'nimkar b'erkecha. If you don't redeem it,
then the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash will sell it to somebody else
and get the proceeds, but you should redeem it. One of the
reasons that is given for this, not just as the פסוק pasuk
is because when you redeem it you add 20%. So therefore, or
25%, depending on how you do the math, anyway, a fifth. Therefore,
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash obviously is better off if you redeem
it. So it's both you have a right to redeem it first,
right? It's sort of like when you sell something at a pawn
shop, right? Don't you get like a ticket? I don't know. But
anyway, from what I understand, and then you have the first right
in order to buy it back before somebody else because maybe you
want to get your property back. So to some degree it's a
right, but it's also a responsibility. We would like you to redeem
it first because that way, A, it's in the תורה Torah and
B, the פסוק pasuk the way it frames it and B, the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash gets more money if you are the one
who redeems it. Okay. הדרן עלך הלוקח ועובר חמורות. Hadran alach Halokeiach
v'Ubar Chamoros. So that's the end of the entire discussion of פטר
חמור. peter chamor. Basically, everything, almost everything there is to say, there's
maybe one line in
one גמרא Gemara elsewhere, but pretty much everything there is to say
about פטר חמור, peter chamor, everything
in the גמרא Gemara was said here. Obviously, more commentaries come later,
but that's the entire discussion. It is interesting I should say, I'll
just say one comment about this last point about מצות עריפה. mitzvas
arifah. The רמב"ם Rambam counts מצות עריפה mitzvas arifah as one of
the תרי"ג מצוות. taryag mitzvos. He actually says in ספר המצוות, Sefer
HaMitzvos, why am I counting the מצוה mitzvah of giving the פדיון
pidyon
of the sheep and עריפה arifah as two separate מצוות? mitzvos?
Aren't they really
like variations of the same מצוה?
mitzvah? And he says, yeah, I probably would have, but because normally
like details of a מצוה mitzvah are counted within one מצוה, mitzvah,
but because this משנה mishnah he says calls it מצות עריפה, mitzvas
arifah, that sounds like it's a different מצוה. mitzvah. So he counts
it as a different מצוה. mitzvah. The ראב"ד Ra'avad actually takes offense
at the רמב"ם Rambam pretty much just quoting the משנה mishnah. and
saying, how could you call this a מצוה? mitzvah? This isn't a
מצוה, mitzvah, this is if somebody did the wrong thing, this is
how they should be punished, and we can't call it a מצוה.
mitzvah. So with these interesting questions, some of the מפרשים meforshim say
just because you call it a מצוה mitzvah doesn't mean it's a
good thing. They say there's like a מצוה mitzvah about how a
man divorces his wife if he's choosing to divorce his wife, doesn't
mean that it's the right thing that he's doing or whatever, now
it depends on the context, but how do you go about it
if you've made this choice, which is maybe not the choice you
should make, but here's how you go about it. But it's interesting
that the ראב"ד Ra'avad takes offense at this being called a מצוה
mitzvah even though that's what it's called in the משנה. mishnah Okay.
Now we move on to what's going to focus most of our
attention for this פרק, perek, which is the firstborn of sheep and
goats and cows, which are brought as קרבנות. korbanos. So let's take
a look. הלוקח עובר פרתו של עובד כוכבים. Halokeiach ubar paraso shel
oved kochavim. If somebody take, now this first משנה mishnah is almost
the exact parallel of the first משנה Mishnah by donkeys, except here
it is by cows. And the basic argument point is that if
a non-Jew owns any part of the mother or of the child,
that you are exempt from the מצוה mitzvah of firstborn. and it
is not a קרבן. Korban. So let's take a look. הלוקח עובר
פרתו של נכרי. Halokei'ach ubar parato shel nochri. You buy the fetus
of a cow of a non-Jew, but the non-Jew owns the cow.
והמוכר לו, Vehamocheir lo, or you sell him the fetus. And now
he's a partner, he's an owner in the actual firstborn. אף על
פי שאינו רשאי, Af al pi she'eino rashai, you're not allowed to
sell him large animals, as we discussed before, even fetuses. והמשתתף לו,
Vehamishtateif lo, or you go into partnership with him, so he's a
part owner. והמקבל ממנו, Vehamakabel mimenu, or you take it in קבלנות,
kablanut, you are going to take care of the cow and raise
the children and you get a part ownership in the children, but
he has a part owner—he owns the cow and he has a
part ownership in the children. והמוסר לו בקבלה, Vehamoseir lo bekabalah, or
he's raising the children and he gets part ownership in the children.
In any of these ways, he's a part—at least a part owner
in the mother or in the child, and that is enough to
exempt you. פטור מן הבכורה, Patur min habechorah, you are exempt, שנאמר
בישראל, Shene'emar beYisrael, it says that I have sanctified for me the
firstborn in Israel, אבל לא באחרים, Aval lo ba'acherim, not amongst non-Jews.
כהנים ולויים חייבים. Kohanim uLeviyim chayavim. And now, again, in contrast to
the משנה Mishnah, we had by donkeys, כהנים ולויים Kohanim uLeviyim who
have firstborn sheep or cattle or flock, have to bring it as
a קרבן. Korban. Why? שאף שלא נפטרו מבכור בהמה טהורה, She'af shelo
nifteru mibechor behemah tehorah, they are not exempt from the firstborn of
kosher animals, אלא מפדיון הבן ומפטר חמור. Ela mipidyon haben umipeter chamor.
They're exempt from redemption, so they don't do the redeeming of the
firstborn because their whole thing of, the way there was that swap
in the desert, right, of the firstborn לויים Leviyim from the firstborn
of humans. So they don't redeem their own firstborn, and they don't
redeem firstborn animals because there was a swap there as well. And
the redemption of firstborn animals is connected to redemption of firstborn humans.
So the כהנים ולויים Kohanim uLeviyim don't do redeeming of the firstborn
humans or animals, but they do do, when it's a kosher animal,
the sanctity of the firstborn to bring as a קרבן. Korban. Let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara מאי איריא דתני פטר חמור
ברישא והדר תני עובר פרתו? Mai irya detani peter chamor bereisha vehadar
tani ubar parato? Why do we start by פטר חמור peter chamor
and then we move on to the firstborn of the cow? ליתני
ברישא עובר פרתו, Litni bereisha ubar parato, mention first the firstborn of
the cow, דקדושת הגוף היא, dekdushat haguf hi, that that's an intrinsic
sanctity and it's brought as a קרבן. והדר ליתני פטר חמור, Vehadar
litni peter chamor, and then talk about donkeys way at the end,
דקדושת דמים היא, dekdushat damim hi, it's only an issue—again, it's interesting
the use of the phrase of sanctity, right? We never really fully
got an answer to that of whether you use a concept of
sanctity by firstborn donkeys. It is forbidden in benefit, but is there
really a concept of sanctity? But anyway, here at least the גמרא
Gemara means, okay, there at least you don't have rights to use
it and the כהן gets the redeemed object, but it's not like
it has—so it's calling that קדושת דמים. kdushat damim. Technically, it's not
the same, but anyway, but it's not קדושת הגוף, kdushat haguf, it's
not like it has intrinsic sanctity to be brought as a קרבן.
So let's talk about firstborn of the animals, which is obviously the
more central topic. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמרי במערבא, Amri bima'arava,
they say in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אי בעית אימא, ei ba'it
eima, if you want, I can say, איידי דחביבא ליה לרבי חנינא.
aidi dechaviva lei l'Rabbi Chanina. First of all, we like the idea
of donkeys because of Rabbi Chanina's דרשה. drasha. If you remember, Rabbi
Chanina's דרשה drasha is why were donkeys singled out? Because they were
the ones that helped us take all the wealth out of Egypt.
So, therefore, somehow we like that דרשה. drasha. Maybe we like the
idea that donkeys helped us get a lot of wealth or maybe
we just like the דרשה, drasha, oh, that's a good idea. It's
a little unclear what exactly is attractive, makes us a very dear
idea. But anyway, either that, or אי בעית אימא, ei ba'it eima,
the one that mostly what's quoted is the second explanation here. איידי
דזוטרן מיליה, Aidi dezutran milei, because it's so short, it's only one
פרק, perek, right? דבהמה טמאה, debehemah tmeiah, that's a very short, small
discussion. פסיק ושדי ליה, Pasik veshadei lei, we chop it off and
we throw it out. Okay, doesn't literally throw it out, but I
mean, sometimes you do that. I do that sometimes. I say, let's
first take care of the small topic, get that out of the
way, and then we'll spend our time talking about the much larger
topic. So, therefore, we get rid of חמור. chamor. There's different ideas
there. We like it enough, we like it a lot, or we
just want to get rid of it. We don't, not necessarily we
like it, but let's get done with it and then move on.
By the way, very, very often פרקים, prakim, מסכתות masechtot begin with
more side topics before they get to more central ones. It could
just be also—the גמרא Gemara doesn't really say this, but it could
be the more central topics were more well-known. So maybe you wanted
to address a more interesting—if you're in the know, the side topics
are a little more interesting, you're less familiar with them. So maybe
it's not as good for the uninitiated, but maybe that was more
interesting for the people that were already initiated. Anyway, that's what the
גמרא Gemara says. Moving on. אמר רבי יצחק בר נחמני אמר ריש
לקיש משום רבי אושעיא, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Nachmani amar Reish Lakish
mishum Rabbi Oshaya, ישראל שנתן מעות לעובד כוכבים ובהמתו ביד עובד כוכבים,
Yisrael shenatan ma'ot l'oveid kochavim uvehemto beyad oveid kochavim, דנים בדיניהם. danim
bedineihem. Now we get into a fascinating digression—not a—I shouldn't even say
a digression. It's not a digression on the משנה, but it's very
central to our discussion. Remember what I told you before about how
nowadays we sell the ear of the cow to a non-Jew and
therefore we get off of the whole מצוה, mitzvah, and I showed
you there was this huge, tiny print or whatever, pages and pages
of summaries of תשובות teshuvot about how do you do a sale
to a non-Jew to make it halakhically effective, because that is a
critical question. Basically, it comes up in a few places, some—a lot
of them having to be workarounds, selling חמץ, chametz, selling ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael for שמיטה, and selling the ear of the cow for
the firstborn. So how do you do a sale that is a
binding sale? What type of sales work between Jews and non-Jews? That's
going to be the focus of the discussion now. So let's take
a look. אמר רב גידל אמר רב, Amar Rav Gidel Amar Rav,
אמרי לה, Amrei lah, ריש לקיש Resh Lakish משום בר קפרא, mishum
bar Kappara, ישראל שנתן מעות לעכו"ם בבהמתם בדיניהם. Yisrael shenatan maot la'akum
be'behemtam bedineichem. So if a Jew gives money to a non-Jew to
get to buy his flock in their law, we will discuss what
that phrase means in a moment, for now let's bracket it, אף
על פי שלא משך קנה, af al pi shelo mashach kana, even
though he has not drawn the flock to him, he owns it
as soon as the money is given. So the money is what
effects the transaction, וחייבת בבכורה, vechayavet bivchora, and then it's obligated in
the firstborn, because if it then gives birth even before he's drawn
the flock to him, when does the sale happen, when does the
transaction happen? When the money is given. That's when it shifts ownership
and that's when the firstborn now will become obligated. And similarly in
the reverse, ואכו"ם שנתן מעות לישראל בבהמתם בדיניהם. ve'akum shenatan maot l'Yisrael
be'behemtam bedineichem. If a non-Jew gives money to a Jew to purchase
the Jew's flock in their laws, we'll see what that means in
a minute, אף על פי שלא משך, af al pi shelo mashach,
same point, even though he has not drawn the flock to him,
קנה kana as soon as the money is given he owns now
the flock. And therefore if from this point out after that money
is given if any firstborn is born, ופטור מן הבכורה, upatur min
habechora, you're exempt from the firstborn because it's owned by the non-Jew.
So the upshot being the very central point to these question of
non-Jewish ownership, what effects the ownership, what effects the transaction? The giving
of money, not the drawing of the object to you. Of course,
it will not remain that simple. So let's take a look. אמר
מר, Amar mar, said the master, meaning recording what we just said
before, ישראל שנתן מעות לעכו"ם בדיניהם, Yisrael shenatan maot la'akum bedineichem, אף
על פי שלא משך, af al pi shelo mashach, even if you
didn't draw the object, קנה, kana, you own it when you give
the money, וחייבת בבכורה, vechayavet bivchora, if you're the one buying it
then it becomes obligated in firstborn. מאי בדיניהם? Mai bedineichem? What is
the meaning of that key phrase "in their laws"? אי נימא בדיניהם
בגופיה, Ee neima bedineichem begufiya, maybe you're saying בדיניהם, bedineichem does that
mean you're stipulating that it takes place in their laws? We're just
describing that the reason the money works from Jews and non-Jews is
that it follows the normal laws that apply. What does it mean
the normal laws that apply? The normal laws that apply when I
am buying not the object of non-Jews but actually when we're buying
and selling people as slaves, both non-Jews to Jews and Jews to
non-Jews, as we'll see. So let's take a look. אי נימא Ee
neima בדיניהם bedineichem, בגופיה, begufiya, the law that applies to their body,
ואתי בקל וחומר, ve'ati bekal vachomer, and then you could make a
קל וחומר. kal vachomer. אם גופו קנה ליה ישראל בכסף, Im gufo
kanei lei Yisrael bechesef, if a Jew can acquire a non-Jewish slave
with money, money does the transaction, דכתיב dechtiv לרשת אחוזה, lereshet achuza,
as it says in the Torah when it speaks about non-Jewish slaves
"you will have them as an inheritance to bequeath as an inheritance",
הקישו כתוב לאחוזה, hikishu katuv leachuza, so it compares slaves to a
normal type of inheritance, a plot of land. מה אחוזה ניקנית בכסף
ובשטר ובחזקה, Ma achuza niknit bechesef u'veshtar u'vachazaka, the same way we
know land is acquired, and we take it for granted that this
is true even of non-Jews, תוספות Tosafot says maybe it's when one
Jew is buying a non-Jewish slave from another Jew, so if a
Jew is buying a land from another Jew, we know how do
you buy land? בכסף ובשטר ובחזקה, Bechesef u'veshtar u'vachazaka, you buy it
with either money or with a writ, with a document, or with
an act of demonstrating ownership, going in and starting to fix up
the field. אף עבד כנעני נקנה בכסף, Af eved kenaani nikna bechesef,
so therefore we say similarly that when you are buying a non-Jew,
at least when you're buying him from a Jew, maybe even when
you're buying it from a non-Jew, but anyway you can buy a
non-Jew through the giving of money. So if you can take possession
of a non-Jew himself through the giving of money, ממונו לא כל
שכן, mamono lo kol sheken, how much more so can you take
possession of property through the giving of chattel through the giving of
money? So first of all that's a weird קל וחומר kal vachomer
because anybody who's learned קידושין Kiddushin or whatever קניינים kinyanim knows that
there are different, you know, different קניינים kinyanim are appropriate for different
types of objects and we don't make these types of קל וחומר,
kal vachomer, but nevertheless the גמרא Gemara, is going to say maybe
בדיניהם bedineichem means the same way it works to acquire them as
slaves with money, you acquire their property with money. One minute. אם
כן אפילו בשטר ובחזקה נמי, Im ken afilu beshtar u'vachazaka nami, if
that's true you should acquire their chattel with שטר shtar and חזקה,
chazaka, and we know that that's not true. ועוד, Ve'od, and even
more than that, ישראל מישראל יוכיח, Yisrael miYisrael yoichiach, I'll prove to
you that you don't make these types of קל וחומר. kal vachomer.
Talk about when a Jew buys from a Jew, דגופיה קנה ליה
בכסף, degufiya kanei lei bechesef, you can buy a Jewish slave, right,
the Torah speaks about Jewish slaves and we know that a way
a Jewish slave is purchased is also through money. So that is
effected through money, but ממונו במשיכה, mamono bemeshicha, but you don't buy
property from a Jew through money, what effects the transaction by chattel
is משיכה. לא meshikha lo. דאורייתא de'oraita קאמרינן, we're getting to that
right now, we're assuming not, we're assuming that based on the way
it works is the way it's דאורייתא as well. Okay, we'll get
to, we're going to get there in a minute. The whole point
is why even start with that, but we'll get there. Okay, so
anyway it can't be that we're saying since money works to acquire
people as slaves it should work for their chattel, there's no קל
וחומר kal vachomer like that. אלא אמר אביי, Ela amar Abaye, rather
Abaye says, בדיניהם שפסק להם תורה, bedineichem shepasak lahem Torah, it just
means that's the law. It doesn't mean like the same law that
applies to x applies to y. It means why does money work
by buying property from non-Jews? Because that's what the Torah says, that
when you, even though for Jews you acquire property by drawing it,
משיכה, meshicha. by taking it close to you, by non-Jews it comes
through money. דכתיב, Dechtiv, how do you know that? It says: או
קנה מיד עמיתך, o kanei miyad amitecha, or if you purchase something
from the hand of your neighbor. your neighbor meaning your fellow Jew.
מיד, miyad, so from your hand means it sounds like the object
is changing hands. That's a type of a משיכה, meshicha, taking physical
possession of the object. So we say מיד עמיתך miyad amitecha when
you're buying from your fellow Jew, הוא דבמשיכה, hu debemeshichah, that's when
it's about taking physical possession, משיכה. meshichah, הא מיד עובד כוכבים, ha
miyad oved kochavim, so therefore with a non-Jew it's different. So if
it's not physical possession, what is it? בכסף, bekessef, that's by money.
Now Tosafot says why are those the only two we're looking at?
Why don't we say שטר, shtar, why don't we say חליפין? chalipin?
So Tosafot says look, when you're dealing with cattle, there are really
two things that happen when you buy cattle. One person gives the
money and the other person takes possession of the object. So there's
כסף kessef and there's משיכה. meshichah. משיכה meshichah. meaning generically taking possession
of the object. So therefore when we are going to assume that
those are always the fundamental two that are sort of the primary
two that are in the discussion. So if the Torah says from
a Jew it's through taking possession of the object and it emphasizes
through a Jew yes, non-Jew is different, so the alternative is the
other part of the transaction of the giving of the money. So
it's the giving of the money that's effective for a non-Jew. So
the Gemara says one minute, ואימא מיד עובד כוכבים כלל כלל לא,
ve'eima miyad oved kochavim klal klal lo, why don't I say no,
maybe from a non-Jew you can't do any transactions? That would make
life hard. So the Gemara says אמר רמי לא סלקא דעתך, amar
rami lo salka datach, that doesn't make sense. קל וחומר kal vachomer
הוא, hu, there a קל וחומר kal vachomer really does work. גופו
קונה, gufo koneh, if you're allowed to take possession of their body,
ממונו לא כל שכן mamono lo kol sheken certainly you should be
able to take possession of their property. So the Torah would not
have prohibited any form of transaction with their property. ואימא, ve'eima, okay,
but still let me say מיד עובד כוכבים עד דאיכא תרתי, miyad
oved kochavim ad de'ika tartei, maybe a Jew it's only possession of
the property is sufficient whereas a non-Jew you have to have both
the money and taking possession. אמרי amri they say no, ולאו קל
וחומר הוא, velao kal vachomer hu, here too we'll use the קל
וחומר. kal vachomer. גופו באחת, gufo be'achat, when you take possession of
his person you only need one, כסף, kessef, you don't need actual
physical possession for the transaction to take place. ממונו בשתים mamono bishtayim
when it's his property, not even his body, you need two acts
to take possession? That doesn't make sense. One act should suffice. ואימא,
ve'eima, okay, but still say או בהא או בהא, o beha o
beha, maybe a Jew it's only through משיכה, meshichah only through taking
possession and a non-Jew maybe it's either one or the other. Maybe
we should read the verse that way. No, דומיא דעמיתך, dumya de'amitecha,
just like it is with a Jew it's with a non-Jew. מה
עמיתך בחדא, ma amitecha bechada, the same way with a Jew it's
one way of transacting and only one, אף עובד כוכבים נמי בחדא
af oved kochavim nami bechada by a non-Jew as well one and
only one. So basically what we're saying is the Torah says how
do you take possession of property from a Jew, how do you
effect the transaction with a Jew, by taking possession of property, by
משיכה, meshichah, and therefore that's only by a Jew. Non-Jew is different
but parallel. What's different but parallel? One act but not another, and
therefore the other act when talking about cattle is the giving of
money. So for a Jew it's with משיכה, meshichah, a non-Jew it
is with כסף. kessef. Now Michael realizes that there's a debate of
רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש Rabbi Yochanan veReish Lakish exactly on this point
of what is the classic transaction with a Jew which we're going
to get to, but now we are assuming that biblically the classic
transaction with a Jew is משיכה meshichah, and therefore it is the
reverse by a non-Jew it is money and that is the assumption
of our ברייתא braita and therefore when it comes to the question
about when do you own the cattle of a non-Jew or vice
versa when does the non-Jew own, it goes by money. Okay that
is where we are now. Now we're going to look at the
second half of this ברייתא, braita, אמר מר, amar mar, ועובד כוכבים
שנתן מעות לישראל אבבא דמציעא בדיניהם, ve'oved kochavim shenatan maot le'Yisrael ababa
demetzia bedineihem, then if a non-Jew now was purchasing and has given
money for your flock, אף על פי שלא משך קנה, af al
pi shelo meshach kanah, once he's given the money even without taking
possession he owns. Same point, money works when you buy from him,
it works when he buys from you. Okay what's the line? In
God we trust, all others pay cash. Anyway the Gemara says, so
מאי בדיניהם mai bedineihem according to their law, and then your example
when he takes possession. מאי בדיניהם, mai bedineihem, what does it mean
in their law? Again what's the meaning of that phrase? אי נימא
בדיניהם דגופיה ei neima bedineihem degufei we're going to go through the
same thing. Maybe it means the same way when they take possession
of our person, when we sell ourselves to them as slaves, it
works with money. Therefore with our property it works as money. Again
the comparison of how you sell a slave, how you acquire a
slave to how you acquire property. דגופיה משום דאתי בקל וחומר, degufei
mishum de'ati bekal vachomer, it's a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. גופו של
ישראל קני ליה בכסף, gufo shel Yisrael kani lei bekessef, if a
non-Jew can acquire a Jew as a slave which is possible, which
is in the Torah, דכתיב מכסף מקנתו, dechtiv mikessef miknato, from the
money of the purchase where it talks about redeeming a fellow Jew
who was sold to a non-Jew as a slave, so it indicates
that they were sold through money. ממונו לא כל שכן, mamono lo
kol sheken, how much more so should they acquire our property through
money. Gemara says that doesn't, no, there's no קל וחומר, kal vachomer,
different types of transactions are, you know, are done differently. So Gemara
says ישראל מישראל יוכיחו, Yisrael miYisrael yochichu, word from Jew will prove
you can't make that קל וחומר. kal vachomer. דגופו קני בכסף, degufo
kani bekessef, a Jew buys another Jew as a slave through money,
ממונו במשיכה, mamono bemeshichah, but the property through משיכה, meshichah so you
can't make a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. אלא אמר אביי, ela amar
Abaye, so Abaye says the same thing. או קנה מיד עמיתך, o
kanei miyad amitekha, right? It's the reverse. The first פסוק pasuk Abaye
quoted is if you purchase something. So therefore we're saying the way
you take possession is through משיכה. meshichah, Now it says if you
sell and also mentions מיד. miyad. So you sell by changing hands.
So the same way עמיתך במשיכה amitekha be'meshikha when you sell something
to a fellow Jew, it changes possession by hand or it changes
the transaction is effected by a change by changing hands. הא לעובד
כוכבים, ha le'oved kokhavim, if you're selling it to a non-Jew, right?
Just the reverse of the other case. That case was buying it
from a non-Jew, here selling it to a non-Jew, בכסף, be'khesef, it's
not with משיכה meshikha. with taking physical possession, it is with money.
And then the גמרא Gemara goes to the same thing it did
before. ואימא ve'eima why don't I say לעובד כוכבים כלל כלל לא,
le'oved kokhavim klal klal lo, you cannot sell anything to a non-Jew?
אמר לי לאו קל וחומר? amar li lav kal vachomer? One minute,
it's a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. גופו קנה, gufu kanei, if you
can sell your body to a non-Jew, ממונו לא כל שכן? mamono
lo kol sheken? Certainly you can sell your cattle, your property. ואימא
ve'eima why don't I say לעובד כוכבים עד דאיכא תרתי? le'oved kokhavim
ad de'ika tartei? Maybe a non-Jew has to do both acts to
take possession of your property? אמר לאו קל וחומר? amar lav kal
vachomer? One minute, it's a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. גופו באחת ממונו
בשתים? gufu be'akhat mamono be'shtayim? If the body, you can sell yourself
as a slave, it's only one act. How would you think that
when you're selling your property it needs two acts? So okay, so
therefore it can't be that. ואימא או בהא או בהא? ve'eima o
be'ha o be'ha? Maybe when you sell to a Jew it's only
by משיכה, meshikha when you sell to a non-Jew he takes possession
either way? So the גמרא Gemara says, no, דומיא דעמיתך. dumya de'amitekha.
Again, parallel to selling to a Jew. מה עמיתך באחת אף עובד
כוכבים באחת. ma amitekha be'akhat af oved kokhavim be'akhat. ומה עמיתך באחת
ve'ma amitekha be'akhat the same way you sell to a fellow Jew
with one transaction, the transaction is משיכה, meshikha, you sell to a
non-Jew with one form of transaction, that transaction is כסף. kesef. So
exactly what we said before. Basically we start by the idea that
you sell to a Jew by משיכה. meshikha, The reverse is true
by a non-Jew. The only the opposite equal and opposite part of
a transaction of cattle is money, is כסף. kesef. And therefore כסף
kesef will determine non-Jewish ownership for the law of בכור. bekhor. And
that's where we are right now. But the question is whether we
end there. So let's take a look a little bit further. ולאמימר
דאמר משיכה בעובד כוכבים קונה. u'le'Amemar de'amar meshikha be'oved kokhavim konei. One
minute, according to אמימר Amemar who says that משיכה meshikha. works by
a non-Jew, not כסף. kesef. So he rejects this entire ברייתא. braita.
Now it's not a problem that אמימר, Amemar, although he's an אמורא,
Amora, rejects the ברייתא braita because as we're going to see, there's
anyway a long-standing debate what really works for a Jew, what really
works for a non-Jew. So okay, there's this ברייתא braita has the
position of כסף kesef for a non-Jew. אמימר Amemar has the position
of משיכה. meshikha But now we want to understand how does he
interpret the פסוק? pasuk? Because the פסוק pasuk says that what works
for a Jew is what does it what works for a non-Jew
is the opposite of what works for a Jew. So if אמימר
Amemar says that a non-Jew is משיכה, meshikha. that would mean that
a Jew is with כסף. kesef. Is that really true? So let's
take a look. ולאמימר דאמר משיכה בעובד כוכבים קונה הניחא אי סבר
לה כרבי יוחנן u'le'Amemar de'amar meshikha be'oved kokhavim konei hani kha i
savar lah ke'Rabbi Yochanan דאמר דבר תורה מעות קונות. de'amar devar Torah
maot konot. Biblically money is what works for a Jew. So it
actually does work. משיכה meshikha, לא. So and משיכה meshikha does not
work according to the תורה Torah for a Jew. Just the מיד
עמיתך, miyad amitekha, the you give the money from hand to hand.
We'll get to it. Yeah, I mean right. And right actually yeah,
it כסף kesef means right, meaning it's it means that you right,
you give the money, right, it's not talking about the actual act
of transaction. So הני לעמיתך לעמיתך? hani le'amitekha le'amitekha? So לעמיתך le'amitekha
is coming to tell you לעמיתך בכסף לעובד כוכבים במשיכה le'amitekha be'khesef
le'oved kokhavim be'meshikha to tell you exactly that. Jews work with money,
non-Jews work with משיכה. meshikha. Now in practice what the rabbis did
is they came along and said that there are practical reasons why
we don't want כסף kesef to work, right? We don't right, exactly.
There are reasons because if you only do it with money then
you'll come to take possession of the property it'll be destroyed, etc.
So everybody's better off if the transaction only takes effect once the
property gets into your possession. That's דרבנן. derabbanan. But biblically it's כסף
kesef for a non-Jew, משיכה meshikha for a Jew. So that works.
And then practically for us now it would be משיכה meshikha both
for Jews and for non-Jews because we leave the non-Jews the way
they were with משיכה meshikha and we rabbinically changed the Jews from
כסף kesef to משיכה. meshikha. That's what אמימר Amemar says. That works.
אלא אי סבר לה כריש לקיש דאמר משיכה מפורשת מן התורה. ella
i savar lah ke'Resh Lakish de'amar meshikha meforeshet min haTorah. But one
minute, if he acts like ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, which is the
way אביי Abaye just explained the previous verses, that for a Jew
biblically it's משיכה. meshikha. Now we've got a problem because a non-Jew
is supposed to be the reverse of a Jew. So according to
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish that a Jew is biblically משיכה, meshikha, how
do we wind up with a non-Jew being sorry, that does work.
Yeah, how does אמימר Amemar wind up saying that a non-Jew is
משיכה meshikha as well? It is not the reverse. So לעמיתך במשיכה
ולעובד כוכבים במשיכה? le'amitekha be'meshikha u'le'oved kokhavim be'meshikha? If you're going to
tell me according to אמימר Amemar that a Jew is משיכה, meshikha,
which is what ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says, and a non-Jew is
משיכה, meshikha, which is what אמימר Amemar says, so לעמיתך למה לי?
le'amitekha lama li? Why is the verse saying to your fellow Jew?
That suggests that the way of transaction to a Jew is different
than the form לעמיתך אתה מחזיר אונאה ואי אתה מחזיר אונאה לכנעני.
le-amitecha ata machzir ona ve-ee ata machzir ona le-chnani. Ah, not for
the beginning of the verse. The beginning of the verse says או
קנה מיד עמיתך. o kanoh mi-yad amitecha. It's the end of the
verse. אל תונו איש את אחיו, al tonu ish et achiv, do
not overcharge. So אמימר Ameimar says you're right. A Jew acquires with
משיכה, meshichah, a non-Jew acquires with משיכה. meshichah. Why does the verse
say לעמיתך? le'amitecha? Not to tell you that there are different forms
of acquisition, but to tell you that the prohibition of overcharging applies
only to a Jew, not to a non-Jew. And if you did
overcharge a Jew, you have to give the money back. If you
overcharge a non-Jew, you do not have to give the money back.
Now, as you can imagine, this is a very difficult גמרא Gemara
both, you know, from a moral perspective, an ethical perspective, and also
from a PR perspective, in terms of what happens if non-Jews, you
know, read this גמרא, Gemara which actually happened in the time of
the Middle Ages where there were Jewish משומדים, meshumadim, apostates, who went
and told the church all the bad stuff in the גמרא Gemara
about non-Jews. So you will notice you always know a גמרא Gemara,
is... the normal phrase in the גמרא Gemara. for non-Jews that we're
familiar with is עכום, Akkum, which is a worshiper of stars. Actually,
the original phrase in the גמרא Gemara is not עכום, Akkum, it's
נכרי nochri or גוי, goy, but we did an act of self-censorship
when the church started burning the גמרות, Gemaras, in order to fix
it ourselves so they would not find things offensive and have a
reason to either edit it or worse, burn it, is we changed
it all the time from גוי goy or נכרי nochri to עכום,
Akkum, star-worshiper. So we said, oh, it's not referring to contemporary non-Jews.
When it got to the really disturbing גמרות, Gemaras, we didn't suffice
with that euphemism and we took a euphemism that made it even
much, much more unrelated to contemporary non-Jews. And therefore we used כנעני.
Knani. So you know in the גמרא Gemara, talks about כנעני, Knani,
that it's really something offensive. And it primarily talks about it, not...
again, that's our printed גמרא, Gemara our edited גמרא. Gemara The original
גמרא Gemara says גוי. goy. The ראשונים Rishonim's גרסא girsa is גזל
גוי gezel goy or אונס גוי. onas goy. But of course, in
our גמרא, Gemara when it talks about the issue about stealing or
overcharging, it speaks about גזל gezel and אונאה ona of a כנעני.
Knani. Okay, so therefore it says that's why it is coming... that's
what it is coming to do. So the גמרא Gemara just ends
by to say that it's not the same for... well, just leave
it at כנעני. Knani. So the גמרא says, I would just stay
by this, obviously we can't give a whole שיעור shiur right now
about attitudes towards non-Jews about these issues, but I will say that
already starting in the time of the ראשונים, Rishonim, and here not
just the מאירי, Meiri, other ראשונים Rishonim as well, and continuing well
into the כתבי אחרונים, kitvei Achronim, even when there were questions about
how you treated Christianity as עבודה זרה avoda zara or not, issues
about this, which had to do with sort of like civil disparity
between the laws and so on, whether it was about damages or
stealing or whatever, were very... you know, very early on got modified
and was said this does not apply to people that are basically
law-abiding, it does not apply to contemporary non-Jews and so on. And
it seems clear that they did not just say that because of
the censor, that they were very, very sincere about that. And anyway,
the מסקנא maskana in גמרא בבא קמא Gemara Bava Kamma is that
גזל gezel of a non-Jew is forbidden. Okay, so let's take a
look, let's just read... Oh, sorry, so you're saying over here... let's
hear... גזל gezel is forbidden? Well, no, so the גמרא is going
to say, well, no, אונאה ona is not. So let's... let's just
read one more line, I don't want to be over, but we
read one more line. The גמרא says like this: ואימא זו אונאה
לכנעני. ve-eima zo ona le-chnani. ולכנעני מאל תונו איש את אחיו נפקא.
ve-li-chnani me-al tonu ish et achiv nafka. Oh, wait, why do you
need it to say לעמיתך? le-amitecha? The end of the verse says
don't overcharge one man his brother. It says brother. So no, חד
לכנעני וחד להקדש. chad le-chnani ve-chad le-hekdesh. One for a non-Jew, a
כנעני, Knani, let's say, and one for הקדש. hekdesh. דצריכא, de-tzricha, and
that you can... that there's no prohibition of overcharging הקדש, hekdesh, which
is pretty wild, right? Which certainly doesn't come from a lack of
respect for הקדש, hekdesh, it's just a categorical exclusion. So therefore also
not for a כנעני. Knani. דצריכא, de-tzricha, you need two verses. דאי
כתב רחמנא חדא, de-i katav rachamana chada, just say one, הוה אמינא
לכנעני הוא דלא אונאה. hava amina le-chnani hu de-la ona. I would
have said, okay, maybe for a כנעני. Knani. אבל הקדש יש לו
אונאה, aval hekdesh yesh lo ona, by הקדש hekdesh of course I
should be prohibited. קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, so it tells
two. The גמרא says: הניחא למאן דאמר גזלו אסור. ha nicha le-man
de-amar gezelo asur. One minute, if you say stealing from a כנעני
Knani is forbidden, היינו דאיצטריכא למישרי אונאה. hainu de-itztricha le-mishrei ona. Therefore
it had to say overcharging, which is not as bad as stealing,
that's permissible. אלא אי סברת למאן דאמר גזלו של כנעני מותר. ela
i savrat le-man de-amar gezelo shel chnani mutar. If you held that
stealing was permitted, אונאה מי באעי? ona mi ba'ei? You don't need
a verse to permit overcharging, that's less than stealing. So אמר, you
know what, you're right. אי סברת למאן דאמר גזלו מותר, i savrat
le-man de-amar gezelo mutar, if you're of the opinion that stealing is
actually permitted from a כנעני, Knani, על כרחך כרבי יוחנן סבירא ליה.
al korchacha ke-Rabbi Yochanan sevira leh. Then you're right, then the only
thing לעמיתך le-amitecha can be doing is contrasting the forms of purchase.
And therefore we have to say, since אמימר Ameimar says that the
purchase from a non-Jew is through משיכה, meshichah, he must hold like
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, the way you purchase from a Jew is
through כסף. kessef. So just to wrap up and we'll continue with
this tomorrow, but the important question about not the גזל gezel and
אונאה, ona, which is very troubling and important, we'll leave that to
what we do in בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, but to focus on
the issue of how you do acquisition, so there's a basic assumption
that the way you acquire from a Jew is different from a
non-Jew. There's a debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש,
Resh Lakish, which is the principal way you acquire from a Jew,
which leads to this question of what's the... principal way you buy
it from a non-Jew. The first ברייתא braita taught you buy from
a non-Jew with כסף. kesef. אמימר Ameimar says you buy from a
non-Jew with משיכה. meshicha. This is an all-important question when it comes
to things like I said, like חמץ, chametz, like היתר מכירה, heter
mechira, and like בכור. bechor. And although רש"י Rashi is of the
opinion like the first ברייתא braita that it's with כסף, kesef, and
he says the way you have to do a transaction for בכור
bechor to sell the ear of the mother is through money in
order the overwhelming position of the ראשונים Rishonim is that it's through
משיכה meshicha like אמימר, Ameimar, and that a Jew is with כסף
kesef biblically and a non-Jew is with משיכה, meshicha, and therefore the
way you sell the animal in order to be exempt is through
an act of משיכה. meshicha. We actually try to do both in
order to cover our bases, so you both do it with money
and with משיכה, meshicha, but anyway, but that remains a very key
question להלכה, l'halacha, what is the act of transaction with a non-Jew,
which is critical for all of these הלכות halachot and particularly this
הלכה of exemption from the בכור. bechor. So to be continued tomorrow.
Okay, so let's see where we ended yesterday.